<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en">
<title type="text">Smile and Know</title>
<subtitle type="text">A Blog.</subtitle>
<generator uri="https://github.com/mojombo/jekyll">Jekyll</generator>
<link rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" />
<link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://localhost:4000" />
<updated>2020-05-03T07:17:50+02:00</updated>
<id>http://localhost:4000/</id>
<author>
  <name>Bastian Hagedorn</name>
  <uri>http://localhost:4000/</uri>
  <email>hagedornbastian@gmail.com</email>
</author>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[On writing and having written]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://localhost:4000/articles/on-writing-and-having-written" />
  <id>http://localhost:4000/articles/on-writing-and-having-written</id>
  <published>2020-04-30T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2020-04-30T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Bastian Hagedorn</name>
    <uri>http://localhost:4000</uri>
    <email>hagedornbastian@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;!--- Recently, I came across a quote that immediately stood out to me:  --&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I don’t like to write, but I take great pleasure in having written. &lt;br /&gt;
– William Zisser (Writing to Learn)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t consider myself a writer, but I know this feeling all too well:
I don’t like to work out, but I take great pleasure in having worked out.
I don’t like to get up early in the morning, but I take great pleasure in starting my day early.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes, the opposite is just as true:
I do like to eat sweets, but I regret having eaten them.
I do like to gossip, but I despise having gossiped.
I do like to procrastinate, but I loathe staring at the same task in my list that just does not seem to disappear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s the same question every time:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Do you overcome the obstacle in the current moment, or do you give in and seek immediate pleasure?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The more time there is between challenge and delayed gratification, the harder it is to withstand the temptation to give in.
Getting up early in the morning for instance, is easy because as soon as I sit in my armchair 15 minutes later, starting my day reading a book in silence with dimmed lights in the living room while the sun slowly rises outside, I remember it was totally worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other challenges require more willpower and discipline.
Working out for example, is a lasting and recurrent challenge that is physically exhausting - by definition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Pain is inevitable. Suffering is optional. &lt;br /&gt;
– Haruki Murakami (What I Talk About When I Talk About Running)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Working out is tiring in the moment, leaves you exhausted, and sometimes rewards you with an aching body the next day.
To make matters worse, it takes consistency over an extended period of time in order to see the results.
Without endorphins flooding your body after exercising, it would be torturous to keep up with a consistent exercise routine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The later in the day it is, the harder it is to withstand challenges too.
People call this willpower depletion and they argue that willpower behaves like a muscle:
You use a little of your finite willpower-strength for every challenge you face throughout your day.
The more challenges we face, the more tired your willpower muscle is in the evening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key to not giving in is to not be challenged in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;I brainwashed myself into craving discomfort. &lt;br /&gt;
– David Goggins (Can’t Hurt Me)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Setting up systems, routines, and habits allows to mindlessly do what you set yourself up to.
Work out the same time every day, be it first thing in the morning or immediately after work, no matter what.
Make all important things opt-out in the calendar.
Try Matt D’Avella’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bfLHTLQZ5nc&quot;&gt;Two Day Rule&lt;/a&gt; where you’re allowed to skip one day but never two in a row.
Make it a question about identity rather than the action:
Are you simply the person who avoids eating processed sugar in general, or do you constantly use willpower to actively decide against it in the moment? 
Figure out what works for you.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually it’s about finding something to blame.
It’s about avoiding the need to decide because something has already decided for you:
“Sorry, I’ve got to work out today since I already skipped yesterday and I’m following the two day rule”.
“It’s 5am - time to meditate like I do every day”, or “Desert? No thanks, I’m avoiding processed sugars.”
Oh, and please don’t say it out loud. 
You don’t want to be someone preaching his personal system to everyone else without having been asked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding systems that work for you is an ongoing process of experimentation.
It’s not gonna be easy and there will be multiple setbacks but&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It’s time to go to war with yourself. &lt;br /&gt;
– David Goggins (Can’t Hurt Me)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;


  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/articles/on-writing-and-having-written&quot;&gt;On writing and having written&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Bastian Hagedorn at &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000&quot;&gt;Smile and Know&lt;/a&gt; on April 30, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[On progressive and maintaining tasks]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://localhost:4000/articles/on-progressive-and-maintaining-tasks" />
  <id>http://localhost:4000/articles/on-progressive-and-maintaining-tasks</id>
  <published>2020-04-28T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2020-04-28T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Bastian Hagedorn</name>
    <uri>http://localhost:4000</uri>
    <email>hagedornbastian@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;!---
Let me oversimplify and say that there are two kinds of tasks you're dealing with everyday.
Task that maintain things and tasks that allow you to progress.

Tasks that maintain things tend to be recurring and restore the order.
I think about thinks like washing clothes, cleaning up the kitchen, taking trash out etc.
They maintain a certain order and just have to done.

Progressive tasks however, make somethings better instead of restoring the old status.
Progressive tasks improve something in a way that makes it a certain bit better than it was yesterday.
I think about things like putting up a new shelf or planting something in your garden.

--&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/articles/on-progressive-and-maintaining-tasks&quot;&gt;On progressive and maintaining tasks&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Bastian Hagedorn at &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000&quot;&gt;Smile and Know&lt;/a&gt; on April 28, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>


<entry>
  <title type="html"><![CDATA[On consuming and creating]]></title>
  <link rel="alternate" type="text/html" href="http://localhost:4000/articles/on-consuming-and-creating" />
  <id>http://localhost:4000/articles/on-consuming-and-creating</id>
  <published>2020-04-08T00:00:00+02:00</published>
  <updated>2020-04-08T00:00:00+02:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Bastian Hagedorn</name>
    <uri>http://localhost:4000</uri>
    <email>hagedornbastian@gmail.com</email>
  </author>
  <content type="html">&lt;!---
Assume your next hour is completely free and you've got no urgent tasks to take care of. 
How do you spend it? 
Do you pick up a book? 
Do you listen to a podcast? 
Do you browse the latest headlines? 
Or instead, do you learn to cook something for sharing it with loved ones? 
Do you start working on this project you've been postponing? 
Do you create or do you consume?

One end of this spectrum is unreachable: 
One cannot create without ever consuming. 
However on the other end, there are black holes: 
people who endlessly take in everything without returning, that is creating, anything. 
I'm a black hole. This is my attempt to change this.

It's about what and how much to take in versus how to procees and what to make of it. 
Regardless of how mindfully one chooses what to consume, the ratio stays the same as long as there's nothing actively created. 
The emphasis is on &quot;actively&quot;. 
Obviously my consumption greatly influences me personally. 
By extension it then also somewhat affects the people close to me. 
One could argue that me influencing others this way is already creating something in someone.

However, this active way of consuming but passive way of &quot;creating&quot; seems unbalanced and feeds an increasing urge to create something as actively and as mindfully as I consume. 
This is it. 
This is my collection of thoughts.
--&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000/articles/on-consuming-and-creating&quot;&gt;On consuming and creating&lt;/a&gt; was originally published by Bastian Hagedorn at &lt;a href=&quot;http://localhost:4000&quot;&gt;Smile and Know&lt;/a&gt; on April 08, 2020.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
</entry>

</feed>